<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Psython</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-09-08T20:00:00+01:00</updated><subtitle>Psychology, Python, PhD</subtitle><entry><title>The Mindshift.</title><link href="/python.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-08T20:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-08T20:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Spider</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-09-08:/python.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thinking about coding&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, for some reason, you've decide decided that learning python would be a good thing to do. Great! I agree with you completely. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well... of course I do or this site would be pointless... &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're going to get to the cool stuff in a minute but before we crack on I want to try to get an idea into your head that will be useful. For a lot of people nowadays, the process of using a computer, or phone, is the process of finding the right button and asking &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paranoia_(role-playing_game)"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friend Computer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to do something for you, and quite often, that's ok. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for people who actually work on computers learning to code allows you to take on a slightly different mindset: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You're not asking the computer to do something, you're &lt;em&gt;telling&lt;/em&gt; the computer what to do.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my experience teaching people data analysis with SPSS, I often see students "beseaching" the software to work, fearfully proffering thier data, seeking out the right buttons and then struggling to parse the output into an assignment or a paper, while not having a conceptual grasp of whats happening in the background. When using something like python, however, you are literally giving the computer instructions, you're the &lt;strong&gt;boss&lt;/strong&gt;. The computer is working for you, doing your bidding. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is that a subtle difference? Sure, but it's a meaningful one. Instead of being stuck with what the computer gives you, you tell it what you want, and (eventually) where you want it, and in what format. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So while I understand that people find learning to code to be intimidating, I want to ask you to see yourself as the hero of this journey. 
 Not like the barbarian, more like the wizard. You will learn what you, get better and better, and slay all kinds of Dragons.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I dunno about you, but I'd rather be using tools and bending things to my will... I mean... being proactive. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So buckle up traveler and lets get to gettin'.&lt;/h2&gt;</content><category term="Python"></category><category term="introduction"></category><category term="mindset"></category></entry><entry><title>Actually Starting</title><link href="/python_start.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-08T20:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-08T20:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Spider</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-09-08:/python_start.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Getting the ball rolling&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What follows is not 100% accurate. I'm using language that makes sense to people who don't have a background in computers. I know that there are terms like "object" and "class" that are more accurate, but if you already know those terms, then this page ain't for you. Feel free to stick around though.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting started in python&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing you need to do is make sure that python is installed on your computer and up to date. There's a few ways to do this, and if you have a Mac it's already there, but your fastest bet is to install &lt;a href="https://www.anaconda.com/distribution/"&gt;anaconda&lt;/a&gt;, which installs python and a few good programs that let you write and run code. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These programs are called &lt;a href="https://www.dummies.com/programming/java/what-is-an-integrated-development-environment/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrated Development Environments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but don't worry about that right now. The short version is they let you work on projects without needing to have loads of windows open on your computer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have installed anaconda, open it up and you'll be presented with a grid of different "apps" (that's not the right term but we're gonna use it here) laid out in a grid. Now, you're free to use any of these apps and there's loads of reason to use each one, but I'm going to work in spyder because... well just because. I was advised to use spyder when I started out, and although I've moved on since, I'm advising you to do the same. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So click "launch" on the spyder app and away we go... &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt Text" src="/images/Spyder.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spyder consists of 3 seperate panes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The text editor, this is where you can write and edit code. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The console, where your code runs (hopefully)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 3rd pane, which does multiple things, like let you view your variables and plots, find files etc. It's a good pane, I like it. It's kinda why we're using spyder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The text editor.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I'm going to assume that you have edited text before, you've used Word, or written a facebook post/tweet? Well in it's simplest terms the text editor is like a word page or a status box. You write in it, you can delete, jump around, copy and paste, the general texty-things. In general you want to write code in here but you can include everyday language as well when you want to explain something, but we'll get to that later. What you need to take away from this is the text editor is like Word or Pages, you write your "document" (in this case some code) and can freely edit it from there. The cool thing is that you can tell the computer to read what you have written in the text editor and take&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Console.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The console is where the magic happens. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Python"></category><category term="introduction"></category><category term="variables"></category></entry><entry><title>Welcome Traveller!</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-06T20:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-06T20:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Spider</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-09-06:/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Don't call it an abstract.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My name is Kev and I'm a PhD student in the social sciences. I won't bore you with the details of my life but I will say that you are welcome and I hope you find something here that is useful to you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site has a two-fold moral purpose. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To document my journey into &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/"&gt;python&lt;/a&gt; and programming in general.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To help others if I can. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short version is, the more I worked with &lt;strong&gt;SPSS&lt;/strong&gt; the more frustrated I became with it. Being of a technical bent, I decided to take the plunge and start using the little bit of programming knowledge I had to escape the monotony of copying and pasting and using my &lt;em&gt;human eyeballs&lt;/em&gt; to read data. Between one thing and another I decided that I would learn python and make that my tool of choice, and within a few weeks I was completely sold to the point of evangelising it where ever I could. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I completed a few data projects with python, wrote a few scripts, read a few books and the people around me were pretty impressed by the results, but, I kept coming up against the same issue time and again...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;"I'm not technical enough to do that, it's cool though..."&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I know these people, they are much smarter than me, more diligent, and they can all spell betterer, so I decided there must be something I can do to help that isn't another long rant about how much better things are with just a few lines of code inder your belt. If you can write a letter, or a post-it or an &lt;em&gt;academic paper&lt;/em&gt; you can definitely write code. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thus, this site.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim is to introduce people to tools like python, git, and markdown that will genuinely make life easier, and to do so in language that humans will understand. This won't be the &lt;a href="https://nostarch.com/pythoncrashcourse2e"&gt;"&lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt;" introduction&lt;/a&gt; because there are much smarter people out there than me, who are really good at programming. But one of the things I've noticed while learning from those people is that they tend to take some steps for granted, steps that are &lt;em&gt;"obvious"&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is, when you start out, a lot of these things really aren't obvious, or at least it can take time for them to become obvious, and if they're skimmed over or they don't click quickly, it can easily leave you feeling like an idiot. Fortunately, I'm really good at feeling like an idiot and I have a healthy dose of background rage that helps me to push past that feeling until I can get something to work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also really enjoy teaching, I love that feeling you get when something clicks into place, and I love seeing that "a-ha" look people get when something clicks for them. For that reason I like breaking things down to find the bit that experts forget to tell you because it's "obvious". It's normally that bit that keeps people stuck, and when that's the case it takes someone making it explicit and then some amount of practice before its "obvious" to you too. My aim here is to try to make that whole loop more enjoyable by taking the bits that were &lt;em&gt;hidden by obviousness&lt;/em&gt; and pointing them out where I can. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have a full plan going in, but I do have &lt;a href="https://spider-z3r0.github.io/python.html"&gt;an idea&lt;/a&gt;, so I'm just going to run with that. If you want to you can run along beside me.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you are interested stick around. If you're not then that's ok too but I hope that you do start using python and some of the &lt;a href="hhttps://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BCQHnlnPusY"&gt;other&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.sublimetext.com/"&gt;tools&lt;/a&gt; out there that let you go beyond Word, Excel, and SPSS becuase life's way more fun over here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kev. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Home"></category><category term="first"></category></entry></feed>