<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Psython - Home</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/home.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-09-06T20:51:00+01:00</updated><subtitle>Psychology, Python, PhD</subtitle><entry><title>Welcome Traveller!</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-06T20:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-06T20:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Spider</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-09-06:/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Don't call it an abstract.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My name is Kev and I'm a PhD student in the social sciences. I won't bore you with the details of my life but I will say that you are welcome and I hope you find something here that is useful to you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site has a two-fold moral purpose. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To document my journey into &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/"&gt;python&lt;/a&gt; and programming in general.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To help others if I can. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short version is, the more I worked with &lt;strong&gt;SPSS&lt;/strong&gt; the more frustrated I became with it. Being of a technical bent, I decided to take the plunge and start using the little bit of programming knowledge I had to escape the monotony of working with SPSS. Between one thing and another I decided that I would learn python and make that my tool of choice, and with a few weeks I was completely sold to the point of evangelising it where ever I could. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I completed a few data projects with python, wrote a few scripts, read a few books and the people around me were pretty impressed by the results, but, I kept coming up against the same issue time and again...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;"I'm not technical enough to do that, it's cool though..."&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I know these people, they are much smarter than me, more diligent, and they can all spell betterer, so I decided there must be something I can do to help that isn't another long rant about how much better things are with just a few lines of code inder your belt. If you can write a letter, or a post-it or an &lt;em&gt;academic paper&lt;/em&gt; you can definitely write code. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thus, this site.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim is to introduce people to tools like python, git, and markdown that will genuinely make life easier, and to do so in language that humans will understand. This won't be the &lt;a href="https://nostarch.com/pythoncrashcourse2e"&gt;"&lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt;" introduction&lt;/a&gt; because there are much smarter people out there than me, who are really good at programming. But one of the things I've noticed while learning from those people is that they tend to take some steps for granted, steps that are &lt;em&gt;"obvious"&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is, when you start out, a lot of these things really aren't obvious, or at least it can take time for them to become obvious, and if they're skimmed over or they don't click quickly, it can easily leave you feeling like an idiot. Fortunately, I'm really good at feeling like an idiot and I have a healthy dose of background rage that helps me to push past that feeling until I can get something to work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also really enjoy teaching, I love that feeling you get when something clicks into place, and I love seeing that "a-ha" look people get when something clicks for them. For that reason I like breaking things down to find the bit that experts forget to tell you because it's "obvious". It's normally that bit that keeps people stuck, and when that's the case it takes someone making it explicit and then some amount of practice before its "obvious" to you too. My aim here is to try to make that whole loop more enjoyable by taking the bits that were &lt;em&gt;hidden by obviousness&lt;/em&gt; and pointing them out where I can. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have a full plan going in, but I do have &lt;a href="https://spider-z3r0.github.io/category/mindshift.html"&gt;an idea&lt;/a&gt;, so I'm just going to run with that. If you want to you can run along beside me.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you are interested stick around. If you're not then that's ok too but I hope that you do start using python and some of the &lt;a href="hhttps://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BCQHnlnPusY"&gt;other&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.sublimetext.com/"&gt;tools&lt;/a&gt; out there that let you go beyond Word, Excel, and SPSS becuase life's way more fun over here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kev. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Home"></category><category term="first"></category></entry></feed>