<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Psython - Python</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/python.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-09-08T20:00:00+01:00</updated><subtitle>Psychology, Python, PhD</subtitle><entry><title>The Mindshift.</title><link href="/python.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-08T20:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-08T20:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Spider</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-09-08:/python.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thinking about coding&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, for some reason, you've decide decided that learning python would be a good thing to do. Great! I agree with you completely. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well... of course I do or this site would be pointless... &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're going to get to the cool stuff in a minute but before we crack on I want to try to get an idea into your head that will be useful. For a lot of people nowadays, the process of using a computer, or phone, is the process of finding the right button and asking &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paranoia_(role-playing_game)"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friend Computer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to do something for you, and quite often, that's ok. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for people who actually work on computers learning to code allows you to take on a slightly different mindset: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You're not asking the computer to do something, you're &lt;em&gt;telling&lt;/em&gt; the computer what to do.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my experience teaching people data analysis with SPSS, I often see students "beseaching" the software to work, fearfully proffering thier data, seeking out the right buttons and then struggling to parse the output into an assignment or a paper, while not having a conceptual grasp of whats happening in the background. When using something like python, however, you are literally giving the computer instructions, you're the &lt;strong&gt;boss&lt;/strong&gt;. The computer is working for you, doing your bidding. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is that a subtle difference? Sure, but it's a meaningful one. Instead of being stuck with what the computer gives you, you tell it what you want, and (eventually) where you want it, and in what format. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So while I understand that people find learning to code to be intimidating, I want to ask you to see yourself as the hero of this journey. 
 Not like the barbarian, more like the wizard. You will learn what you, get better and better, and slay all kinds of Dragons.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I dunno about you, but I'd rather be using tools and bending things to my will... I mean... being proactive. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So buckle up traveler and lets get to gettin'.&lt;/h2&gt;</content><category term="Python"></category><category term="introduction"></category><category term="mindset"></category></entry></feed>